<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<dataset descriptor="kinyarwanda">
  <file id="kmc00365" languages="kin,eng,fra">
    <metadata interviewer="Yves" interviewee="Murekatete Seraphine" date="" location="Kicukiro" otherInfo=""/>
    <data>
      <unit time="00:00:54" speaker="Yves"><align>
        <text langid="kin"><s>Ushobora kutubwira amazina yanyu?</s></text>
        <text langid="eng"><s>Could you please tell us your name?</s></text>
        <text langid="fra"><s>Pourrais-tu nous dire ton nom s'il te plat?</s></text>
      </align></unit>
      <unit time="00:00:55" speaker="Serafina"><align>
        <text langid="kin"><s>Njyewe  nitwa Murekatete Serafina, nkaba mbere y'intambara mu ntambara nari ntuye hano mu kagali, mbere kari Gasharu ya kabiri ariko ubu ni Kagina, umurenge wa Kicukiro, akarere ka Kicukiro. Nabaga kwa marume noneho intambara ibaye, turahunga tuva mu nzu twabagamo turahunga tujya mu yindi iri hirya yayo, noneho interahamwe ziraza zihita zidushorera ziratuzana marume bamwicira kuri etaje iri hirya hano.</s></text>
        <text langid="eng"><s>My name is Murekatete Serafina, before the war, i mean during the war i was staying here in this cell, before it was known as Gasharu 'ya kabiri' (gasharu 2) but know it is Kagina, Kicukiro sector,kicukiro district. I was staying at my uncle's place and when the war started, we fled, got out of the house we were staying in and went to another that was close by, and then the Interahamwes came and made us walk, they brought us and my uncle was killed in a building that is close by.</s></text>
        <text langid="fra"><s>Je m'appelle Murekatete Sraphine. Avant la guerre... je veux dire durant la guerre, je vivais ici dans cette cellule. Avant elle tait appele Gasharu II mais aujourd'hui elle s'appelle Kagina, dans le secteur de Kicukiro, et le district Kicukiro. J'habitais chez mon oncle et lorsque la guerre a commenc, nous avons fui de la maison o nous habitions et sommes alls chercher refuge dans une autre maison avoisinante. Les Interahamwes sont venus et nous ont fait marcher et nous ont emmens. Mon oncle a t tu dans un building pas loin d'ici.</s></text>
      </align></unit>
      <unit time="00:01:36" speaker="Serafina"><align>
        <text langid="kin"><s>Baratuzana abandi twari kumwe babicira hano ndumva bararengaga barindwi. Bamaze kubica ubwo njye nahise mbacika, nyura hagati y'amazu hirya aha ngera ku muhanda wa hano hepfo w'igitaka Ubwo interahamwe zarengaga nk'icumi, zahise zimbohoza zimaze kumbohoza zirandarana buracya ndagenda nsubira hepfo y'aho twabaga.</s></text>
        <text langid="eng"><s>They brought us, they killed some people who were with us, they were more than seven. After killing them i escaped them, i passed between houses that are here nearby, i reached the dusty road, then i was raped by more than ten interahamwe, after raping me they spent the night with me, the next day i left and went back to my neighbourhood [closer to where i was staying].</s></text>
        <text langid="fra"><s>Serafina Ils nous ont emmens et ont tu certaines personnes qui taient avec nous. Ils taient plus de 7. Aprs qu'ils les aient tus, je me suis chappe et je me suis glisse entre les maisons dans le voisinage jusqu' une route poussireuse pas loin d'ici. J'ai alors t viole par plus de 10 Interahamwes et ils ont pass la nuit avec moi aprs m'avoir viole. Le jour suivant, je suis retourne dans mon quartier.</s></text>
      </align></unit>
      <unit time="00:02:11" speaker="Yves"><align>
        <text langid="kin"><s>Ahangaha mwatubwiye ko haguye abantu barenga barindwi.</s></text>
        <text langid="eng"><s>Did you say that seven people died here?</s></text>
        <text langid="fra"><s>As-tu dit que 7 personnes ont t tues ici?</s></text>
      </align></unit>
      <unit time="00:02:15" speaker="Serafina"><align>
        <text langid="kin"><s>Haguye abantu barenga barindwi.</s></text>
        <text langid="eng"><s>More than seven people died here.</s></text>
        <text langid="fra"><s>Plus de 7 personnes ont t tues.</s></text>
      </align></unit>
      <unit time="00:02:18" speaker="Yves"><align>
        <text langid="kin"><s>Babiciye hehe?</s></text>
        <text langid="eng"><s>Where were they killed?</s></text>
        <text langid="fra"><s>O ont-elles t tues?</s></text>
      </align></unit>
      <unit time="00:02:19" speaker="Serafina"><align>
        <text langid="kin"><s>Babiciye ahangaha, mbere hari icyapa cya taxi, kuko ubu urabona ko cyimutse cyikajya ahagana haruguru.</s></text>
        <text langid="eng"><s>They were killed here, there was a bus stop sign, but now as you can see it was moved to up there.</s></text>
        <text langid="fra"><s>Ils ont t tus ici, il y avait un panneau d'arrt bus, mais aujourd'hui, il a t dplac un peu plus haut d'ici comme vous pouvez le voir.</s></text>
      </align></unit>
      <unit time="00:02:28" speaker="Yves"><align>
        <text langid="kin"><s>Abantu babishe bari abantu bameze gute? bari abasirikare?</s></text>
        <text langid="eng"><s>The people who killed them what were they like? were they soldiers?</s></text>
        <text langid="fra"><s>Comment taient les gens qui les ont tus? Etaient-ils militaires?</s></text>
      </align></unit>
      <unit time="00:02:31" speaker="Serafina"><align>
        <text langid="kin"><s>Bari interahamwe, nta basirikare barimo, bari interahamwe zari zifite imbunda. Abandi bari bafite ibyuma.</s></text>
        <text langid="eng"><s>They were interahamwe, they were no soldiers among them, they were interahamwe with guns others had tools.</s></text>
        <text langid="fra"><s>C'tait des Interahamwes, il n'y avait pas de militaires parmi eux. Ces Interahamwes avaient des armes  feu et des instruments.</s></text>
      </align></unit>
      <unit time="00:02:38" speaker="Yves"><align>
        <text langid="kin"><s>Bageraga nko kuri bangahe?</s></text>
        <text langid="eng"><s>How many were they?</s></text>
        <text langid="fra"><s>Combien taient-ils?</s></text>
      </align></unit>
      <unit time="00:02:41" speaker="Serafina"><align>
        <text langid="kin"><s>Bageraga nko kw'icumi, nibo badushoreye mbese.</s></text>
        <text langid="eng"><s>They were like ten, they are the ones who made us walk.</s></text>
        <text langid="fra"><s>Serafina Ils taient  peu prs 10, ce sont eux qui nous ont pouss  marcher.</s></text>
      </align></unit>
      <unit time="00:02:45" speaker="Yves"><align>
        <text langid="kin"><s>Ni nabyo babicishije gusa, babicishije imbunda?</s></text>
        <text langid="eng"><s>Are those the only things they used to kill them, they killed them with guns?</s></text>
        <text langid="fra"><s>Est-ce tout ce qu'ils ont utilis pour les tuer? Les ont-ils tus avec des armes  feu?</s></text>
      </align></unit>
      <unit time="00:02:48" speaker="Serafina"><align>
        <text langid="kin"><s>Barabarashe bose, barabarashe.</s></text>
        <text langid="eng"><s>They shot them all, they shot them.</s></text>
        <text langid="fra"><s>Ils les ont tous tir dessus.</s></text>
      </align></unit>
      <unit time="00:02:51" speaker="Yves"><align>
        <text langid="kin"><s>Babarasiye hehe?</s></text>
        <text langid="eng"><s>Where did they shoot them from?</s></text>
        <text langid="fra"><s>D'o ont-ils tir sur eux?</s></text>
      </align></unit>
      <unit time="00:02:52" speaker="Searafina"><align>
        <text langid="kin"><s>Babarasiye ahangaha imbere ku cyapa, aha ku cyapa cya taxi ku muhanda.</s></text>
        <text langid="eng"><s>They shot them from here in front of the bus stop sign, here at the bus stop sign, at the roadside.</s></text>
        <text langid="fra"><s>Ils leur ont tir dessus devant le panneau  l'arrt bus, ici  l'arrt bus, sur le bas de la route.</s></text>
      </align></unit>
      <unit time="00:02:58" speaker="Yves"><align>
        <text langid="kin"><s>Hano hantu turabona ko ari ku muhanda, iyo muhaciye cyangwa muhanyuze mwigendera, murabyibuka?</s></text>
        <text langid="eng"><s>We can see that it is at the road side, when you pass here do you tend to remember?</s></text>
        <text langid="fra"><s>On peut voir que c'est en bas de la route, lorsque tu passes par ici, as-tu tendance  te rappeler?</s></text>
      </align></unit>
      <unit time="00:03:05" speaker="Serafina"><align>
        <text langid="kin"><s>Turabyibuka cyane cyane ko hanaguyemo ababyeyi, abavandimwe ndetse n'inshuti iyo mpanyuze buri gihe mpita nibuka nkareba kuko mpita nshushanya icyo gihe.</s></text>
        <text langid="eng"><s>We remember so much, because our parents, relatives and friends died from here, everytime i pass here i remember and see because i can picture the time.</s></text>
        <text langid="fra"><s>On se souvient de tellement de choses car nos parents proches et loigns, nos amis sont tous morts ici. Chaque fois que je passe par ici, je me souviens et je revois toute la scne de cette poque l.</s></text>
      </align></unit>
      <unit time="00:03:19" speaker="Yves"><align>
        <text langid="kin"><s>Kuri wowe wifuza ko n'abandi bantu bamenya ko aha hantu haguye abantu?</s></text>
        <text langid="eng"><s>Personally would you like other people to also know that there are some people who died from here?</s></text>
        <text langid="fra"><s>Personnellement, est-ce que tu aimerais que d'autres personnes sachent que certaines personnes sont mortes ici?</s></text>
      </align></unit>
      <unit time="00:03:23" speaker="Serafina"><align>
        <text langid="kin"><s>Yeee, ndabyifuza, njyewe ku bwanjye nifuzako abantu bose, nubwo bigaragara ko ari ku muhanda bahasudirira ko ariko habereye ibintu bibi muri jenoside, abantu barahaguye. Ku bwanjye rero numva ko umuntu wese yahibuka kubera ibyo bibi byahabereye.</s></text>
        <text langid="eng"><s>Yeah, i would really like them to, personally i would like everyone to, even though it is at the roadside to be fenced because bad things happened at the place during the genocide, people died from here, personally therefore i feel everyone should remember this place because of the bad things that took place here.</s></text>
        <text langid="fra"><s>Oui je le veux vraiment. Personnellement je voudrais que tout le monde le sachent. Et mme si c'est sur le bas de la route, que l'endroit soit cltur car de mauvaises choses s'y sont droules. Donc,  mon avis, tout le monde devrait se souvenir de cet endroit  cause de toutes les mauvaises choses qui s'y sont droules.</s></text>
      </align></unit>
      <unit time="00:03:53" speaker="Yves"><align>
        <text langid="kin"><s>Abantu bashyinguwe hano mu ntambara buno bajyanwe hehe?</s></text>
        <text langid="eng"><s>People who were buried here during the war, where were they put afterward?</s></text>
        <text langid="fra"><s>O est-ce que les personnes qui ont t enterres ici durant la guerre ont t emmenes par aprs?</s></text>
      </align></unit>
      <unit time="00:03:57" speaker="Serafina"><align>
        <text langid="kin"><s>Bamwe twarabataburuye tubajyana i Nyanza, abo ba marume twabashije kubajyana iwacu aho tuvuka.</s></text>
        <text langid="eng"><s>We reburied some and took them to Nyanza, we managed to take my uncle where we originate from.</s></text>
        <text langid="fra"><s>Nous avons de nouveau enterr certains d'entre eux  Nyanza. Nous avons pu emmener le corps de mon oncle dans sa rgion d'origine.</s></text>
      </align></unit>
      <unit time="00:06:16" speaker="Serafina"><align>
        <text langid="kin"><s>Nitwa Murekatete Serafina, nari mfite imyaka 26 mu ntambara, interahamwe icyo gihe zaratuzamuzakanye zitujyana muri iyi nzu, ari naho zambohoreje hamwe n'abandi bakobwa twari kumwe. Hanyuma ubwo muri iyi nzu twabagamo hirya aha, bagiye batunyuzaho abantu bagiye kwica babicira hano, aha inyuma yanjye hari urugo hari n'amazu, ngira ngo murabona ko hari umurima ariko mbere hari amazu. Bahiciye abantu batatu.</s></text>
        <text langid="eng"><s>Serafina My name is Murekatete Serafina, i was 26 years old during the war, interahamwe at that time walked us to this house where they raped us, i was together with other girls, we were staying nearby, they used to bring people when they are going to kill and kill them from here, just behind here there was a fence and even houses, you can clearly see that there is a farm, but before there were houses. 3 people were killed from here.</s></text>
        <text langid="fra"><s>Serafina Je m'appelle Murekatete Sraphine, j'avais 26 ans durant la guerre. A l'poque, les Interahamwes nous ont conduits  cette maison et nous ont violes. J'tais avec d'autres jeunes filles qui vivaient dans le voisinage. Ils emmenaient les gens qu'ils voulaient tuer ici et les tuaient ensuite  partir d'ici. Avant, il y avait une clture juste derrire et quelques maisons. Aujourd'hui il y a une ferme mais avant il y avait des maisons. Trois personnes ont t tues ici.</s></text>
      </align></unit>
      <unit time="00:07:09" speaker="Yves"><align>
        <text langid="kin"><s>Mushobora kutubwira abo bantu bari bantu cyi?bari abana, bari abagabo?</s></text>
        <text langid="eng"><s>Could you tell us what age group,gender, these people were? were they children or men?</s></text>
        <text langid="fra"><s>Pourrais-tu nous dire l'ge et le genre des personnes qui taient ici? Etaient-ils des enfants ou des hommes?</s></text>
      </align></unit>
      <unit time="00:07:14" speaker="Serafina"><align>
        <text langid="kin"><s>Umwe yari umugabo wubatse, undi yari umusaza ariko udakuze cyane, undi nawe yari umugabo.</s></text>
        <text langid="eng"><s>One was a man with a family, the other one was an old man but not very elderly, the other was also a man.</s></text>
        <text langid="fra"><s>Un d'entre eux tait pre de famille, un autre tait vieux mais pas trs vieux, il y avait aussi un autre homme.</s></text>
      </align></unit>
      <unit time="00:07:24" speaker="Yves"><align>
        <text langid="kin"><s>Bishwe n'abantu ki? Interahamwe cyangwa abasirikare ?</s></text>
        <text langid="eng"><s>Who killed them? Interahamwe? Or soldiers?</s></text>
        <text langid="fra"><s>Qui les a tus? Les Interahamwe? Ou les militaires?</s></text>
      </align></unit>
      <unit time="00:07:27" speaker="Serafina"><align>
        <text langid="kin"><s>Bishwe n'interahamwe kubera ko abasirikare bo ntago bari bakunze kuba bari hano, bari hakurya muri camp GP, abandi bari hirya hariya kwa Majyambere hano hari higanje interahamwe nyinshi cyane. Ku buryo arizo zabazamukanaga zibatunyuranaho hariya hirya aho twari turi.</s></text>
        <text langid="eng"><s>They were killed by interahamwe, because soldiers were rarely here, they were in republican guard barracks, others were on the other side at majyambere's place, this place was mostly occupied by many interahamwe, who walked the peope who were going to be killed .</s></text>
        <text langid="fra"><s>Ce sont des Interahamwes qui les ont tus car les soldats se trouvaient rarement ici. Ils se trouvaient dans les barraques de la Garde Rpublicaine, de l'autre ct, chez Majyambere. Ce quartier tait principalement occup par des Interahamwes qui conduisaient les gens sur le lieu des massacres.</s></text>
      </align></unit>
      <unit time="00:07:52" speaker="Yves"><align>
        <text langid="kin"><s>Abo bantu bishwe bate?</s></text>
        <text langid="eng"><s>How were those people killed?</s></text>
        <text langid="fra"><s>Comment les tuaient-ils?</s></text>
      </align></unit>
      <unit time="00:07:55" speaker="Serafina"><align>
        <text langid="kin"><s>Abo bantu barabarashe.</s></text>
        <text langid="eng"><s>They were shot.</s></text>
        <text langid="fra"><s>Ils les ont tirs dessus.</s></text>
      </align></unit>
      <unit time="00:08:00" speaker="Yves"><align>
        <text langid="kin"><s>Ushobora kutubwira umubare w'abantu baje kubafata uko banganaga, ugereranyije niba mukibyibuka?</s></text>
        <text langid="eng"><s>Can you please tell us the number of the people who came for you, approximate if you remember?</s></text>
        <text langid="fra"><s>Peux-tu nous dire le nombre des gens qui sont venus vous chercher s'il te plat? Essaye d'estimer s'il te plait.</s></text>
      </align></unit>
      <unit time="00:08:04" speaker="Serafina"><align>
        <text langid="kin"><s>Umubare w'interahamwe, izakoraga hepfo hariya twabanje, ni nazo zakomeje gukora na hano kuko zari zimwe, zari nyinshi rwose ku buryo zagabaga igitero ukabona ari nyinshi.</s></text>
        <text langid="eng"><s>The number of interahamwe, the ones who worked down the road, are the same ones who worked even here, they were very many, they would make a big squad.</s></text>
        <text langid="fra"><s>Le nombre des Interahamwes ceux qui travaillaient le long de cette route, les mmes qui 'travaillaient' ici taient trs, trs nombreux, ils constituaient une grande escouade.</s></text>
      </align></unit>
      <unit time="00:08:24" speaker="Yves"><align>
        <text langid="kin"><s>Hanyuma uru rugo uhita ubona ko habaga abantu, abantu ba hano barabishe? Ni nabwo bahasenye icyo gihe?</s></text>
        <text langid="eng"><s>One can see that people lived here, were these people killed? Was the house destroyed at that time?</s></text>
        <text langid="fra"><s>Il est evident que des gens vivaient ici, ces gens ont-ils t tus? La maison a-t-elle t dtruite en ce moment?</s></text>
      </align></unit>
      <unit time="00:08:31" speaker="Serafina"><align>
        <text langid="kin"><s>Oya, ntago babishe kubera ko inzu zari iz'umuntu ubungubu zari zishaje ubungubu ngire ngo n'uko zasenyutse, ariko nyirazo arahari.</s></text>
        <text langid="eng"><s>No, they were not killed, the houses were old and I think they broke down, but the owner is still alive.</s></text>
        <text langid="fra"><s>Non, ils n'ont pas t tus, les maisons taient vieilles et je crois qu'elles se sont croules mais le propritaire est toujours en vie.</s></text>
      </align></unit>
      <unit time="00:08:43" speaker="Yves"><align>
        <text langid="kin"><s>Izi nazo bazisenye mu ntambara?</s></text>
        <text langid="eng"><s>and were those destroyed during the war?</s></text>
        <text langid="fra"><s>Et celles-l, ont-elles t dtruites durant la guerre?</s></text>
      </align></unit>
      <unit time="00:08:45" speaker="Serafina"><align>
        <text langid="kin"><s>Oya, zarishenye kubera kuzifata nabi, cyangwa se no kutabyitaho banza ariyo mpamvu zasenyutse.</s></text>
        <text langid="eng"><s>No, they broke down, because of poor maintenance, and caring less I think that is why they broke down</s></text>
        <text langid="fra"><s>Non, elles se sont croules par manque d'entretien et d'intrt. Je crois que c'est ce qui a conduit  leur ruine.</s></text>
      </align></unit>
      <unit time="00:08:55" speaker="Yves"><align>
        <text langid="kin"><s>Aha hantu ndumva harabereye ibintu bitari byiza, hariciwe abantu, iyo mwebwe muhageze ubungubu nyuma ya jenoside hababwira iki?</s></text>
        <text langid="eng"><s>Bad things happened in this place, people were killed from here, when you reach here after the Genocide what does it mean to you?</s></text>
        <text langid="fra"><s>De mauvaises choses se sont droules ici, des gens ont t tus ici, qu'est-ce que tu ressens lorsque tu viens ici depuis la fin du genocide?</s></text>
      </align></unit>
      <unit time="00:09:06" speaker="Serafina"><align>
        <text langid="kin"><s>Kubera ko, ntago nkunze kuhagera, kuhahita, ariko hirya aha hari akayira iyo mpahise mpita nibuka ko hano twari duhari no mubyo nganira mba mbivuga kuko ntazabyibagirwa, kuko twahaboneye ibintu bitari byiza kandi ibintu biteye ubwoba n'agahinda, ku buryo rero ntashobora kubyibagirwa niyo byagenda gute.</s></text>
        <text langid="eng"><s>I rarely pass here, but nearby there is a short cut when I pass there, I always remember that we were once here, even in my conversations am always talking about it because I will never forget, we saw things that were not good, scary and sad things, and that is why I cannot forget no matter what.</s></text>
        <text langid="fra"><s>C'est rare que je passe par ici mais il y a un raccourci pas loin d'ici et chaque fois que je passe par l, je me souviens que nous y tions un jour. Mme dans mes conversations je n'arrte pas d'en parler car je ne l'oublierai jamais. Nous avons vu des choses qui ne sont pas bonnes, des choses qui font peur, des choses tristes et c'est pour cela que je ne peux l'oublier en aucun cas.</s></text>
      </align></unit>
      <unit time="00:09:34" speaker="Yves"><align>
        <text langid="kin"><s>Kuri wowe wifuza ko abandi bantu bamenya ibyabereye hano?</s></text>
        <text langid="eng"><s>Personally would you like people to know what took place here?</s></text>
        <text langid="fra"><s>Personnellement, est-ce que tu aimerais que les gens sachent ce qui s'est droul ici?</s></text>
      </align></unit>
      <unit time="00:09:38" speaker="Serafina"><align>
        <text langid="kin"><s>Yeee, ndabyifuza.</s></text>
        <text langid="eng"><s>Yeah, I do.</s></text>
        <text langid="fra"><s>Oui je le veux.</s></text>
      </align></unit>
      <unit time="00:09:44" speaker="Yves"><align>
        <text langid="kin"><s>Abantu biciwe ahangaha ubu bari hehe? Byagenze gute nyuma ya jenoside?</s></text>
        <text langid="eng"><s>People who were killed from here, where are they buried now? what happened after the genocide?</s></text>
        <text langid="fra"><s>O sont enterrs les gens qui ont t tus ici? Que s'est-il pass aprs le gnocide?</s></text>
      </align></unit>
      <unit time="00:09:50" speaker="Serafina"><align>
        <text langid="kin"><s>Nyuma duhungutse kuko twahungiye i Ndera twaje mbere, twari tuzi aho babashyinguye twarabataburuje, bamwe tubajyana i Nyanza hamwe n'abandi ariko umugabo umwe witwaga Raphal Rwamukwaya yari atuye hariya hirya umuryango we umugore we yari akiriho, amusaba ko yamushyingura mu nzu ye. Ariko nyuma umudamu we yaje gupfa, apfuye ejo bundi igihe ubuyobozi bwavugaga ko nta bantu bagomba guhama mu nzu twamukuyemo tumujyana ku mushyingura ku Gisozi.</s></text>
        <text langid="eng"><s>When we came back from refuge we arrived first because we had fled to Indera  (it's near), we knew where they had been buried, we exhumed them, we took some to Nyanza but one man named Raphael Rwamukwaya who was staying nearby, his family, his wife was still alive and asked to bury him in her house, but after some time his wife died, the other day the authorities said that no body should be left in houses, we exhumed him and took him and reburied him in respect in Gisozi.</s></text>
        <text langid="fra"><s>Lorsque nous sommes revenus d'exil, nous tions les premiers  revenir car nous n'tions qu' Ndera.  Nous savions o ils avaient t enterrs, nous les avons donc exhum pour les emmener  Nyanza mais la famille ainsi que la femme d'un homme appel Raphael Rwamukwaya qui habitait dans les environs taient encore en vie et ils ont demand  l'enterrer dans sa proprit. Aprs quelques temps, sa femme est dcde et dernirement les autorits ont decide que personne ne devrait tre enterr dans des proprits prives, nous l'avons exhum et sommes alls l'inhumer  Gisozi en toute dignit.</s></text>
      </align></unit>
      <unit time="00:10:41" speaker="Serafina"><align>
        <text langid="kin"><s>Hano hepfo ku muhanda ku cyapa cya taxi hiciwe abantu barenga barindwi, bishwe n'interahamwe, izo nterahamwe zabicishije imbunda, babatabye munsi y'umuhanda wa kaburimbo, mbere hari inzu ariko ubu hari ikibanza, hari na atelier yo gusudira ariko bigaragara ko mbere hari hari ikibanza.</s></text>
        <text langid="eng"><s>Down the road at the bus stop sign, seven people were killed from there, they were killed by interahamwe, those interahamwe killed them using guns, they buried them below the tarmac road, there was a house before but it is now empty land, there is a tailor shop but one can clearly see that there was an empty land.</s></text>
        <text langid="fra"><s>En bas de la rue,  l'arrt de bus, 7 personnes ont t tues par des Interahamwes. Ces Interahamwes ont utilis des armes  feu, ils les ont enterr en bas de la route goudronne, il s'y trouvait une maison auparavant mais aujourd'hui il n'y a qu'un terrain vide. Il y a un atelier de couture mais c'est vident qu'il y avait un terrain vide auparavant.</s></text>
      </align></unit>
      <unit time="00:11:16" speaker="Yves"><align>
        <text langid="kin"><s>Abo bantu barindwi bishwe bate?</s></text>
        <text langid="eng"><s>How were those seven people killed?</s></text>
        <text langid="fra"><s>Comment ces 7 personnes ont-elles t tues?</s></text>
      </align></unit>
      <unit time="00:11:18" speaker="Serafina"><align>
        <text langid="kin"><s>Abo bantu barabarashe, barabarashe kubera ko benshi bari bafite imbunda. Bishwe n'interahamwe zarengaga nk'icumi.</s></text>
        <text langid="eng"><s>Those people were shot, they were shot since many had guns, they were killed by more than ten interahamwe.</s></text>
        <text langid="fra"><s>Serafina Ils les ont tirs dessus car beaucoupd d'entre eux avaient dea armes  feu. Ils ont t tus par plus de 10 Interahamwes.</s></text>
      </align></unit>
      <unit time="00:11:34" speaker="Yves"><align>
        <text langid="kin"><s>Ubu hariya hantu mwebwe ko ari ku muhanda, iyo muhanyuze mugenda, wenda muri nko muri taxi mwumva mumeze mute?</s></text>
        <text langid="eng"><s>That place is at the roadside, when you pass the place walking or in a bus what do you feel?</s></text>
        <text langid="fra"><s>Cet endroit se trouve sur la route, qu'est-ce que tu ressens lorsque tu passes par l en bus ou  pied?</s></text>
      </align></unit>
      <unit time="00:11:41" speaker="Serafina"><align>
        <text langid="kin"><s>Iyo tuhaciye kubera ko twanahabaye igihe kirekire, n'ubu akaba ariho dukunda kunyura iyo tuhageze mpita cyane cyane iyo ndikumwe n'umuntu mpita mubwira ngo aha hantu haguye abavandimwe, inshuti n'ababyeyi. Ku buryo rero ntashobora kubyibagirwa.</s></text>
        <text langid="eng"><s>When we pass here, having stayed here for a long time, we still like passing here, when we reach here i emmediatly...especially when i am with someone i emmediatly tell them that i lost my relatives, friends and parents here, and thus i can never forget.</s></text>
        <text langid="fra"><s>Lorsque nous passons par ici.. puisque nous avons vcu ici pendant largement longtemps, nous aimons utiliser ce chemin, et ds que j'arrive ici, je surtout lorsque je suis avec quelqu'un d'autre, je leur dis tout de suite que j'ai perdu mes parents proches et loigns ici et que par consquent, je ne peux jamais oublier.</s></text>
      </align></unit>
      <unit time="00:12:08" speaker="Yves"><align>
        <text langid="kin"><s>Kuri wowe wumva ko n'abandi bantu bamenya nubwo bwose byabereye ku muhanda?</s></text>
        <text langid="eng"><s>Personally do you feel that other people should also know about it even though it happened at the roadside?</s></text>
        <text langid="fra"><s>Est-ce que tu penses que d'autres personnes devraient savoir ce qui s'est droul ici malgr que c'est sur la route?</s></text>
      </align></unit>
      <unit time="00:12:12" speaker="Serafina"><align>
        <text langid="kin"><s>Bamenya ibyahabereye kubera ko ibyahabereye atari byiza kandi nta n'uwifuza ko byakongera kuba.</s></text>
        <text langid="eng"><s>They should know what happened since what happened was not good and no one would wish for it to happen again.</s></text>
        <text langid="fra"><s>Ils doivent savoir ce qui s'est pass puisque ce qui est arrive n'tait pas bon, personne ne souhaiterait que a arrive de nouveau.</s></text>
      </align></unit>
    </data>
  </file>
</dataset>
